ok guys for this problem we're going to
want to generate this compound starting
from benzene using any any other
compounds you want. so as a hint we're probably
gonna be using some electrophilic
aromatic substitution so go ahead and
see if you can build this molecule
ok so let's take a look at the two substituents that are on the target
molecule so first we have an alkyl group
we know that we can attach an alkyl
group onto a benzene ring by Friedel
Crafts alkylation and then we also have
nitration. but what order are we
gonna do them in? in order to answer this
question we have to understand something
about the directing abilities of these
groups. now we know that an alkyl group
is an ortho/para director and we know
that a nitro group is a meta director
and we also understand that this spatial
relationship between them on the
molecule is ortho, so this is gonna tell us
what order we have to do the reactions
in because given that they have an ortho
relationship to one another it must be
the ortho/para director that directed
the other group to its position and so
what we're saying is that we must
starting with benzene have done the
Friedel Crafts alkylation here with this alkyl chloride to get this
intermediate because if we have this
intermediate then upon nitration we will
get a mixture of ortho and para
nitrated products whereas if we were to
do the nitration first if we did the
nitration first and let's say this was
our nitrated product then if we went
and did the alkylation we would get meta
direction from the nitro group and so
the nitro group cannot have been the
compound that was added first because that
will not give us a structure that
matches our target molecule, instead
we're recognizing that alkyl is ortho/para, nitro group is meta, so it must
have been the alkyl group that directed
the nitro group to the ortho position, we
can get this mixture, separate them out
and there is going to be our target molecule
thanks for watching guys, subscribe to my channel for more tutorials, and as always feel free to email me